<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Don’t call me ‘Mellow Yellow’: or daring to be colourful in a world of adults who prefer to wear black. With help from Liz West, The Spice Girls and Joni Mitchell!	</title>
	<atom:link href="/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/</link>
	<description>Supporting children&#039;s language, communication and learning</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 13:24:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.3</generator>
			<item>
				<title>
				By: Michael Jones				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/#comment-7825</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Jones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 15:32:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=810#comment-7825</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Hi Tim
You are in The Curst Sons!! I have visited your website and now I know that you are a mean slide guitar and mandolin player!!
(I am a mean member of audiences that watch bands like yours!)
You have made some very fascinating points there (as usual). Is it really fair to say that many children with ASD are disturbed by colour? There is some wisdom going round that they need to be only in rooms that are totally light blue.
I wonder....
I would love to see how ALL children react to Liz West&#039;s installations. I certainly don&#039;t advocate hugely bright rooms or those that you call &#039;bland&#039; but I think we should all be sensitive to how children respond to colour and light, and use them as a way of helping children and adults enjoy their environment. The natural world can be a very bright place when the sun shines, and people from sunny countries tend to wear very bright clothes, as I discovered in Bangkok recently, and as we see from photos and film of African countries and India.

Regarding your response to music, I certainly agree with you about some people thinking that only so-called &#039;classical&#039; will do, and will only play this type of music when children come into and leave assembly. I was always looking for different types of music to get a response.

One thing I would like to see is children exposed to more live music. They just love it when a teacher plays the guitar and sings (the school piano doesn&#039;t always have the same effect, for some reason).
Trevor Stevens, who I mentioned in my posts about sleep, worked with me in a special school, and he has a real gift of speaking to children through his guitar playing. Steve Grocott, who I have also worked with, is a mandolin player and he also has the same impact on very young children.
Best wishes
Michael
PS I&#039;ve just finished this weekend&#039;s post about Janis Joplin and Cat Stevens!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi Tim<br />
You are in The Curst Sons!! I have visited your website and now I know that you are a mean slide guitar and mandolin player!!<br />
(I am a mean member of audiences that watch bands like yours!)<br />
You have made some very fascinating points there (as usual). Is it really fair to say that many children with ASD are disturbed by colour? There is some wisdom going round that they need to be only in rooms that are totally light blue.<br />
I wonder&#8230;.<br />
I would love to see how ALL children react to Liz West&#8217;s installations. I certainly don&#8217;t advocate hugely bright rooms or those that you call &#8216;bland&#8217; but I think we should all be sensitive to how children respond to colour and light, and use them as a way of helping children and adults enjoy their environment. The natural world can be a very bright place when the sun shines, and people from sunny countries tend to wear very bright clothes, as I discovered in Bangkok recently, and as we see from photos and film of African countries and India.</p>
<p>Regarding your response to music, I certainly agree with you about some people thinking that only so-called &#8216;classical&#8217; will do, and will only play this type of music when children come into and leave assembly. I was always looking for different types of music to get a response.</p>
<p>One thing I would like to see is children exposed to more live music. They just love it when a teacher plays the guitar and sings (the school piano doesn&#8217;t always have the same effect, for some reason).<br />
Trevor Stevens, who I mentioned in my posts about sleep, worked with me in a special school, and he has a real gift of speaking to children through his guitar playing. Steve Grocott, who I have also worked with, is a mandolin player and he also has the same impact on very young children.<br />
Best wishes<br />
Michael<br />
PS I&#8217;ve just finished this weekend&#8217;s post about Janis Joplin and Cat Stevens!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Tim Dunkerley				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/#comment-7824</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim Dunkerley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 12:04:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=810#comment-7824</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I have a problem with colour. I&#039;m apparently &quot;colourblind&quot; Which means that when someone shows me those dotty circles I can&#039;t see numbers, letters or pictures just....dots. It&#039;s apparently only men who are thus afflicted. For me it doesn&#039;t mean I see the world in monotones I can see most colours just not all, especially if they are close in proximity or tone to each other. I can&#039;t read black type on a red blackground, and dammit I&#039;m not allowed to be a fighter pilot.
Interestingly this spills over into my language too, as I have real difficulty naming some colours and sticking to the same names at a later date.
Also it took my wife and I quite a while to realise that when choosing new paints or curtains etc; when I said (eventually) &quot;I really don&#039;t care what colour we choose&quot;, I wasn&#039;t being &quot;male&quot; I literally didn&#039;t have an opinion as apple white and sunflower oat white A) looked pretty much the same to me, even if I squinted and B) more importantly, provoked absolutely no aesthetic or emotional response in me. In a relationship where one shares spaces, best to go with the choices of the person who does have a response to colour then.....rather than me.

On the plus side it did take me quite a long time to realise that potentially the reason I have such strong reactions to music is that I don&#039;t have much of a response to visual stimuli.My brain has compensated. Music moves me more now than it ever did. Some music makes me cry some moves me in other emotional and intellectual ways. It&#039;s not all positive though:My most unappealing habit is a complete intolerance for some music or the artists that produce it. I literally feel myself becoming angry at music that I decide is vacuous or at music that I really like being played too softly. 
Some music actually makes me furious: That somebody should have bothered....I have horrible musical prejudices
I am also extremely intolerant of the implicit view held in some circles that Classical music is &quot;real music&quot; and the rest of music may be charming etc but not as &quot;good&quot; as it isn&#039;t as complicated or technically sophisticated.



I&#039;m always banging on in these responses about sensory modulation and how important background &quot;noise&quot; is. But your (as usual excellent post) makes us all think that colour can be &quot;noise&quot; too. Witness very bland plain classrooms for some pupils with ASC for whom some visual busyness can be, at worst deeply distressing and at best extremely distracting.
Keep up the good work Michael
Tim]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have a problem with colour. I&#8217;m apparently &#8220;colourblind&#8221; Which means that when someone shows me those dotty circles I can&#8217;t see numbers, letters or pictures just&#8230;.dots. It&#8217;s apparently only men who are thus afflicted. For me it doesn&#8217;t mean I see the world in monotones I can see most colours just not all, especially if they are close in proximity or tone to each other. I can&#8217;t read black type on a red blackground, and dammit I&#8217;m not allowed to be a fighter pilot.<br />
Interestingly this spills over into my language too, as I have real difficulty naming some colours and sticking to the same names at a later date.<br />
Also it took my wife and I quite a while to realise that when choosing new paints or curtains etc; when I said (eventually) &#8220;I really don&#8217;t care what colour we choose&#8221;, I wasn&#8217;t being &#8220;male&#8221; I literally didn&#8217;t have an opinion as apple white and sunflower oat white A) looked pretty much the same to me, even if I squinted and B) more importantly, provoked absolutely no aesthetic or emotional response in me. In a relationship where one shares spaces, best to go with the choices of the person who does have a response to colour then&#8230;..rather than me.</p>
<p>On the plus side it did take me quite a long time to realise that potentially the reason I have such strong reactions to music is that I don&#8217;t have much of a response to visual stimuli.My brain has compensated. Music moves me more now than it ever did. Some music makes me cry some moves me in other emotional and intellectual ways. It&#8217;s not all positive though:My most unappealing habit is a complete intolerance for some music or the artists that produce it. I literally feel myself becoming angry at music that I decide is vacuous or at music that I really like being played too softly.<br />
Some music actually makes me furious: That somebody should have bothered&#8230;.I have horrible musical prejudices<br />
I am also extremely intolerant of the implicit view held in some circles that Classical music is &#8220;real music&#8221; and the rest of music may be charming etc but not as &#8220;good&#8221; as it isn&#8217;t as complicated or technically sophisticated.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m always banging on in these responses about sensory modulation and how important background &#8220;noise&#8221; is. But your (as usual excellent post) makes us all think that colour can be &#8220;noise&#8221; too. Witness very bland plain classrooms for some pupils with ASC for whom some visual busyness can be, at worst deeply distressing and at best extremely distracting.<br />
Keep up the good work Michael<br />
Tim</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Michael Jones				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/#comment-7823</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Jones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2013 22:27:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=810#comment-7823</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Hi Maggie!!! And I was the 13 year old on Guildford station transfixed by all the colourful hippies heading for the festival!!
The whole weekend is captured on an amazing DVD called &#039;Message to Love.&#039; 
That&#039;s amazing!!
The festival is as legendary as Woodstock, and though I wanted to be there, it did look very chaotic. Did it rain at all??
I am writing a series of 12 articles for Early Years Educator magazine, about early language development. I will email you to pick your brains about something.
Great to hear from you!!
Michael]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi Maggie!!! And I was the 13 year old on Guildford station transfixed by all the colourful hippies heading for the festival!!<br />
The whole weekend is captured on an amazing DVD called &#8216;Message to Love.&#8217;<br />
That&#8217;s amazing!!<br />
The festival is as legendary as Woodstock, and though I wanted to be there, it did look very chaotic. Did it rain at all??<br />
I am writing a series of 12 articles for Early Years Educator magazine, about early language development. I will email you to pick your brains about something.<br />
Great to hear from you!!<br />
Michael</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Maggie Harris				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/#comment-7822</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Maggie Harris]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2013 22:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=810#comment-7822</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I can&#039;t believe you have a You Tube of the IoW festival
I was there see if you can spot me. I&#039;m the tall girl with long blond hair. I can&#039;t remember what I was wearing but it would have been bright colours too!!!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I can&#8217;t believe you have a You Tube of the IoW festival<br />
I was there see if you can spot me. I&#8217;m the tall girl with long blond hair. I can&#8217;t remember what I was wearing but it would have been bright colours too!!!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Michael Jones				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/#comment-7821</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Jones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2013 21:58:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=810#comment-7821</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Thank you Carol
I have a lot of fun writing the posts. 
I had a real surprise when Liz West contacted me via Twitter yesterday. I have added some great photos of her work onto the bottom of my post. You just want to get inside those big rooms that are bathed in bright colour. I think colour is so important for all of us, and particularly for children. I love showing them how to mix colours. 
Adults certainly have strong views about wearing yellow, unless you are a Norwich supporter. The Brasil football kit is yellow, and looks great. 
That&#039;s a great story about the Spice Girls. My daughter was a big fan, and in a funny way I think they did a lot for girls&#039; confidence, which is important. 
Thank you for replying
Best wishes
Michael]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you Carol<br />
I have a lot of fun writing the posts.<br />
I had a real surprise when Liz West contacted me via Twitter yesterday. I have added some great photos of her work onto the bottom of my post. You just want to get inside those big rooms that are bathed in bright colour. I think colour is so important for all of us, and particularly for children. I love showing them how to mix colours.<br />
Adults certainly have strong views about wearing yellow, unless you are a Norwich supporter. The Brasil football kit is yellow, and looks great.<br />
That&#8217;s a great story about the Spice Girls. My daughter was a big fan, and in a funny way I think they did a lot for girls&#8217; confidence, which is important.<br />
Thank you for replying<br />
Best wishes<br />
Michael</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Carol Adams				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/#comment-7820</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carol Adams]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2013 19:27:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=810#comment-7820</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Love your blogs; always something to think about. Yellow is my favourite colour but I would never wear it - makes me look ill. When working with the children I try to wear something bright or eye-catching. The children certainly notice - especially the girls. I was also recommended to wear a bright red lipstick so that children focused on your mouth. Perhaps not appropriate in your case although I do have a green wig you can borrow. 

Funny story about the Spice Girls: at the height of their popularity we took my young daughter and a group of her friends to see a Spice Girls tribute act as a birthday treat. They had a great time, especially when &#039;Ginger&#039; got my daughter on stage during the closing number to join in. A year or so later my daughter made a comment about this night out that made my husband and I realise that she thought she had seen the real Spice Girls. My husband and I gave each other worried looks but kept quiet. We did own up when she was in her late teens, but it was like a child finding out Father Christmas doesn&#039;t exist.

Looking forward to a bit of Janis Joplin]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Love your blogs; always something to think about. Yellow is my favourite colour but I would never wear it &#8211; makes me look ill. When working with the children I try to wear something bright or eye-catching. The children certainly notice &#8211; especially the girls. I was also recommended to wear a bright red lipstick so that children focused on your mouth. Perhaps not appropriate in your case although I do have a green wig you can borrow. </p>
<p>Funny story about the Spice Girls: at the height of their popularity we took my young daughter and a group of her friends to see a Spice Girls tribute act as a birthday treat. They had a great time, especially when &#8216;Ginger&#8217; got my daughter on stage during the closing number to join in. A year or so later my daughter made a comment about this night out that made my husband and I realise that she thought she had seen the real Spice Girls. My husband and I gave each other worried looks but kept quiet. We did own up when she was in her late teens, but it was like a child finding out Father Christmas doesn&#8217;t exist.</p>
<p>Looking forward to a bit of Janis Joplin</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Michael Jones				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/#comment-7817</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Jones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 19:19:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=810#comment-7817</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Thank you Julie!
I think that punk taught us in the UK that clothing conventions, like &#039;blue and green should never be seen&#039; are just conventions. I love it when children take an interest in colour, and are allowed to wear colourful clothes. 
I was going up an escalator on the tube (subway) in London once, and everyone was wearing either black or grey, apart from me (red fleece) and an Indian woman (bright blue sari). 

I&#039;m glad you like my posts. I have a notebook with ideas, that are often sparked off by a song, or something from YouTube. Then I link that to an idea I have about communication. I chip away at it during the week and then have it all finished by the weekend.
Edmund, who looks after my website, puts it all together for me on a Saturday morning.
I was on a long haul flight to Bangkok recently, and I was listening to their music selection, and Janis Joplin was on there. This got me to thinking about one of her songs, so my next post might be about that. However I got lost in Bangkok when a taxi driver dropped me at the wrong place, so I might write about that instead!
Best wishes
Michael ]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you Julie!<br />
I think that punk taught us in the UK that clothing conventions, like &#8216;blue and green should never be seen&#8217; are just conventions. I love it when children take an interest in colour, and are allowed to wear colourful clothes.<br />
I was going up an escalator on the tube (subway) in London once, and everyone was wearing either black or grey, apart from me (red fleece) and an Indian woman (bright blue sari). </p>
<p>I&#8217;m glad you like my posts. I have a notebook with ideas, that are often sparked off by a song, or something from YouTube. Then I link that to an idea I have about communication. I chip away at it during the week and then have it all finished by the weekend.<br />
Edmund, who looks after my website, puts it all together for me on a Saturday morning.<br />
I was on a long haul flight to Bangkok recently, and I was listening to their music selection, and Janis Joplin was on there. This got me to thinking about one of her songs, so my next post might be about that. However I got lost in Bangkok when a taxi driver dropped me at the wrong place, so I might write about that instead!<br />
Best wishes<br />
Michael </p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Julie Barton				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/dont-call-me-mellow-yellow-or-daring-to-be-colourful-in-a-world-of-adults-who-prefer-to-wear-black-with-help-from-liz-west-the-spice-girls-and-joni-mitchell/#comment-7816</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Julie Barton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 17:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=810#comment-7816</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[When our children were teenagers, we scheduled an appointment for a family portrait.  We were told not to wear yellow because it does not flatter our skin tones.  

Otherwise, I say wear yellow and be proud of it!

Your blogs are so much fun to read.  How long does it take for you to write each of them?]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When our children were teenagers, we scheduled an appointment for a family portrait.  We were told not to wear yellow because it does not flatter our skin tones.  </p>
<p>Otherwise, I say wear yellow and be proud of it!</p>
<p>Your blogs are so much fun to read.  How long does it take for you to write each of them?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
			</channel>
</rss>
