<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: I’ve got that at home!! The power of sameness for very young children	</title>
	<atom:link href="/2013/03/ive-got-that-at-home-the-power-of-sameness-for-very-young-children/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2013/03/ive-got-that-at-home-the-power-of-sameness-for-very-young-children/</link>
	<description>Supporting children&#039;s language, communication and learning</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 07:59:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.3</generator>
			<item>
				<title>
				By: Julie Barton				</title>
				<link>/2013/03/ive-got-that-at-home-the-power-of-sameness-for-very-young-children/#comment-1214</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Julie Barton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 18:17:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=574#comment-1214</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[As an adult, I still believe in magic.  When I do not understand how something amazing happens, I consider it to be magical.  For an example, when my husband and I bought our computer and installed a router so that we had internet access from our dish throughout the house, I thought the router was magical (I still do). Sometimes, people will provide me with an explanation for how something happens, whether I ask for it or not.  This can spoil the &quot;magic&quot; for me.  I think that all of us would be happier if we experienced a little bit of magic in our lives.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As an adult, I still believe in magic.  When I do not understand how something amazing happens, I consider it to be magical.  For an example, when my husband and I bought our computer and installed a router so that we had internet access from our dish throughout the house, I thought the router was magical (I still do). Sometimes, people will provide me with an explanation for how something happens, whether I ask for it or not.  This can spoil the &#8220;magic&#8221; for me.  I think that all of us would be happier if we experienced a little bit of magic in our lives.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Carolyn Purser				</title>
				<link>/2013/03/ive-got-that-at-home-the-power-of-sameness-for-very-young-children/#comment-1122</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carolyn Purser]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2013 18:18:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=574#comment-1122</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I deliver training on Quality Transitions and suggest that the setting and school should agree on a set of familiar books and songs so when the children start their new school (or move rooms in a day nursery) they immediately recognise some familiar things. Another good idea to make children feel at home is to paint pictures in their old setting then the new one displays them so when the child walks in for the first time, there&#039;s their painting!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I deliver training on Quality Transitions and suggest that the setting and school should agree on a set of familiar books and songs so when the children start their new school (or move rooms in a day nursery) they immediately recognise some familiar things. Another good idea to make children feel at home is to paint pictures in their old setting then the new one displays them so when the child walks in for the first time, there&#8217;s their painting!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Trevor Stevens				</title>
				<link>/2013/03/ive-got-that-at-home-the-power-of-sameness-for-very-young-children/#comment-1105</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Trevor Stevens]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2013 10:58:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=574#comment-1105</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[LOVE this blog! Its so true.
It explains why people buy the boxed DVD set of a whole TV series and why a concert of Beethoven&#039;s 5th always sells out more quickly than Beethoven&#039;s 1st.  Its not only people with autism who like sameness!!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>LOVE this blog! Its so true.<br />
It explains why people buy the boxed DVD set of a whole TV series and why a concert of Beethoven&#8217;s 5th always sells out more quickly than Beethoven&#8217;s 1st.  Its not only people with autism who like sameness!!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Marie Charlton				</title>
				<link>/2013/03/ive-got-that-at-home-the-power-of-sameness-for-very-young-children/#comment-989</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marie Charlton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 22:00:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=574#comment-989</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I think it is more than interesting to find that starting school at four was just as negative an experience for you as it is for children now! Thanks for that valuable bit of first hand experience.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think it is more than interesting to find that starting school at four was just as negative an experience for you as it is for children now! Thanks for that valuable bit of first hand experience.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Steve Grocott				</title>
				<link>/2013/03/ive-got-that-at-home-the-power-of-sameness-for-very-young-children/#comment-986</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Grocott]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 11:13:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=574#comment-986</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Yes this happens with songs a lot - you sing Spiderman or anything that is on  a DVD or television and children are very moved by the fact and exclaim delightedly &quot;I&#039;ve got that at home&quot; It&#039;s a powerful bridge.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yes this happens with songs a lot &#8211; you sing Spiderman or anything that is on  a DVD or television and children are very moved by the fact and exclaim delightedly &#8220;I&#8217;ve got that at home&#8221; It&#8217;s a powerful bridge.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: moriel gidney				</title>
				<link>/2013/03/ive-got-that-at-home-the-power-of-sameness-for-very-young-children/#comment-985</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[moriel gidney]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 09:25:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=574#comment-985</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Thank you again thought provoking once more. I have had some interesting thoughts around the way we present books to the children here - being very very fortunate in the numbers of books we have can actually be a disadvantage for the very young possibly. I have stripped back the selection to far less and specifically make visible those that either we have used in story time or ones we have made this term by using photos of the children around the setting in and out which has led to lots of chats and delight as they see themselves in a &#039;book&#039;. Familiarity maybe another word along the lines of &#039;same&#039;. Starting from where the child is and leading them out - education! (a leading out)
Further challenges for presenting books to children as the precious new journeys of thought they offer.
Thank you!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you again thought provoking once more. I have had some interesting thoughts around the way we present books to the children here &#8211; being very very fortunate in the numbers of books we have can actually be a disadvantage for the very young possibly. I have stripped back the selection to far less and specifically make visible those that either we have used in story time or ones we have made this term by using photos of the children around the setting in and out which has led to lots of chats and delight as they see themselves in a &#8216;book&#8217;. Familiarity maybe another word along the lines of &#8216;same&#8217;. Starting from where the child is and leading them out &#8211; education! (a leading out)<br />
Further challenges for presenting books to children as the precious new journeys of thought they offer.<br />
Thank you!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
			</channel>
</rss>
