<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Did you ever wake up with them bullfrogs on your mind? Helping children to understand their emotions and to learn English, with help from Rory Gallagher and Canned Heat!	</title>
	<atom:link href="/2013/11/did-you-ever-wake-up-with-them-bullfrogs-on-your-mind/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2013/11/did-you-ever-wake-up-with-them-bullfrogs-on-your-mind/</link>
	<description>Supporting children&#039;s language, communication and learning</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 07:59:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.3</generator>
			<item>
				<title>
				By: Michael Jones				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/did-you-ever-wake-up-with-them-bullfrogs-on-your-mind/#comment-7842</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Jones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2013 15:15:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=843#comment-7842</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Hi John!
Yes, I had completely underestimated the impact that a guinea pig can have on young children&#039;s developing emotions. I&#039;m going to look at Igor Presnyakov right now. However you may like to look at Rodrigo and Gabriela as well.
Best wishes
Michael]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi John!<br />
Yes, I had completely underestimated the impact that a guinea pig can have on young children&#8217;s developing emotions. I&#8217;m going to look at Igor Presnyakov right now. However you may like to look at Rodrigo and Gabriela as well.<br />
Best wishes<br />
Michael</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: John Rice				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/did-you-ever-wake-up-with-them-bullfrogs-on-your-mind/#comment-7841</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[John Rice]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2013 08:46:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=843#comment-7841</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[So much of what you say chimes with my own experiences. Year 4 is absolutely the best year to teach - they arrive as small children and leave with a massively developed maturity. Your George story had me hoodwinked!

So I need to investigate Rory Gallagher. A new name for me but I suspect nobody will come close to Igor Presnyakov whose playing has reinterpreted what it is to be a guitarist.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So much of what you say chimes with my own experiences. Year 4 is absolutely the best year to teach &#8211; they arrive as small children and leave with a massively developed maturity. Your George story had me hoodwinked!</p>
<p>So I need to investigate Rory Gallagher. A new name for me but I suspect nobody will come close to Igor Presnyakov whose playing has reinterpreted what it is to be a guitarist.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Tim Dunkerley				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/did-you-ever-wake-up-with-them-bullfrogs-on-your-mind/#comment-7840</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim Dunkerley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2013 11:31:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=843#comment-7840</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[No probs re reply. I love your blogs for their own sake. They are the only interwebbing /networking thing I do apart from read my friend Paul&#039;s tweets.

Rock music &quot;events&quot; were basically a shambles compared to the corporate smoothness of today. Did some of it&#039;s soul get lost in the mud of the Weeley festival? I&#039;m not sure I care, as part of the joy for me has always been it&#039;s disposability.

Rory Gallaghers 1974 tour of Ireland crops up on Sky Arts TV regularly and give or take a few guitar-based  continuity errors is an absolute stormer of a film. (Going to my hometown/hometown blues on the mandolin is pretty epic)

Donal lets guitarists come and play Rory&#039;s guitars. Search Johnny Marr playing that Stratocaster on youtube. Or don&#039;t; it&#039;s maybe a bit too guitar-nerdy. But it does combine two of your guitar heroes in one easy hit.

Memories and films of the cultural currency of (rock) music from the 70&#039;s are a heady brew aren&#039;t they especially for gentlemen and ladies of a certain age. You sort of remember them not quite in black and white, but in  a sort of  developing sepia with  spots of colour bleeding through. Suffused with the smell of a damp afghan coat,the feel of itchy lambswool sweaters, the chafing of uncomfortable loon pants and the faint whiff of patchouli oil.

I too rocked the Rory look and cling to aspects of it today I suspect. (Check shirts and double denim)We invented perpetual teenage so we can do what the hell we like with it. A friend of mine who is a couple of years older than me  once remarked that he thinks his /our generation will be marked out by a strange crew of little old people who have a marked preference for sitting on the floor.

It all becomes a bit complicated with the tribes, generations, genres and sub genres all overlaying on peoples cultural reference points doesn&#039;t it: E.G. Strange for us maybe to  observe the  nostalgic memories of the rave generation and the Stone Roses Spike Island Epiphany(weirdly apparently still a shambles..plus ca change.)

Looking forward to the next blog. I&#039;m predicting an apearance from Roger Daltrey
TDx]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>No probs re reply. I love your blogs for their own sake. They are the only interwebbing /networking thing I do apart from read my friend Paul&#8217;s tweets.</p>
<p>Rock music &#8220;events&#8221; were basically a shambles compared to the corporate smoothness of today. Did some of it&#8217;s soul get lost in the mud of the Weeley festival? I&#8217;m not sure I care, as part of the joy for me has always been it&#8217;s disposability.</p>
<p>Rory Gallaghers 1974 tour of Ireland crops up on Sky Arts TV regularly and give or take a few guitar-based  continuity errors is an absolute stormer of a film. (Going to my hometown/hometown blues on the mandolin is pretty epic)</p>
<p>Donal lets guitarists come and play Rory&#8217;s guitars. Search Johnny Marr playing that Stratocaster on youtube. Or don&#8217;t; it&#8217;s maybe a bit too guitar-nerdy. But it does combine two of your guitar heroes in one easy hit.</p>
<p>Memories and films of the cultural currency of (rock) music from the 70&#8217;s are a heady brew aren&#8217;t they especially for gentlemen and ladies of a certain age. You sort of remember them not quite in black and white, but in  a sort of  developing sepia with  spots of colour bleeding through. Suffused with the smell of a damp afghan coat,the feel of itchy lambswool sweaters, the chafing of uncomfortable loon pants and the faint whiff of patchouli oil.</p>
<p>I too rocked the Rory look and cling to aspects of it today I suspect. (Check shirts and double denim)We invented perpetual teenage so we can do what the hell we like with it. A friend of mine who is a couple of years older than me  once remarked that he thinks his /our generation will be marked out by a strange crew of little old people who have a marked preference for sitting on the floor.</p>
<p>It all becomes a bit complicated with the tribes, generations, genres and sub genres all overlaying on peoples cultural reference points doesn&#8217;t it: E.G. Strange for us maybe to  observe the  nostalgic memories of the rave generation and the Stone Roses Spike Island Epiphany(weirdly apparently still a shambles..plus ca change.)</p>
<p>Looking forward to the next blog. I&#8217;m predicting an apearance from Roger Daltrey<br />
TDx</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Michael Jones				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/did-you-ever-wake-up-with-them-bullfrogs-on-your-mind/#comment-7838</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Jones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2013 07:55:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=843#comment-7838</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Hi Carol
It&#039;s amazing to think that Woodstock was over 40 years ago. As a teenager I was totally fascinated by the whole Woodstock idea. The bands were uppermost in my mind, but the vision of thousands of colourful people all heading in one direction was what really caught my imagination. If it was now I&#039;d be thinking abut the toilets and where I could have a wash and clean my teeth!
I went to the Windsor Free Festival in 1974 and there were no facilities at all! Everyone was horrified, and the festival was eventually broken up by the police after nine days.
Happy days?
Michael]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi Carol<br />
It&#8217;s amazing to think that Woodstock was over 40 years ago. As a teenager I was totally fascinated by the whole Woodstock idea. The bands were uppermost in my mind, but the vision of thousands of colourful people all heading in one direction was what really caught my imagination. If it was now I&#8217;d be thinking abut the toilets and where I could have a wash and clean my teeth!<br />
I went to the Windsor Free Festival in 1974 and there were no facilities at all! Everyone was horrified, and the festival was eventually broken up by the police after nine days.<br />
Happy days?<br />
Michael</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Carol Adams				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/did-you-ever-wake-up-with-them-bullfrogs-on-your-mind/#comment-7837</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carol Adams]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 22:56:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=843#comment-7837</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[The stage at Woodstock was in a very interesting condition; can you imagine bands being allowed to play on that stage today. The Health and Safety fairies would have a field day but have they made things any safer? Saw The Stereophonics at Brighton on Thursday - they had a carpet put down before their performance!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The stage at Woodstock was in a very interesting condition; can you imagine bands being allowed to play on that stage today. The Health and Safety fairies would have a field day but have they made things any safer? Saw The Stereophonics at Brighton on Thursday &#8211; they had a carpet put down before their performance!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Michael Jones				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/did-you-ever-wake-up-with-them-bullfrogs-on-your-mind/#comment-7836</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Jones]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 22:08:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=843#comment-7836</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Thanks Tim! I saw Rory&#039;s guitar in a glass case at the Kilburn Tricycle Theatre premiere of the lost film of his Irish Tour in the 1970s. No one else would play in Belfast, but Rory insisted.
He was extremely popular as a live player. I used to dress like him: checked shirt, baseball boots, blue jeans and waistcoat. It was a real sadness that he passed away. 
I still haven&#039;t answered your question about children with a diagnosis and selective mutism, but will do so.
Very best wishes
Michael
PS this weekend&#039;s post is about stammering.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks Tim! I saw Rory&#8217;s guitar in a glass case at the Kilburn Tricycle Theatre premiere of the lost film of his Irish Tour in the 1970s. No one else would play in Belfast, but Rory insisted.<br />
He was extremely popular as a live player. I used to dress like him: checked shirt, baseball boots, blue jeans and waistcoat. It was a real sadness that he passed away.<br />
I still haven&#8217;t answered your question about children with a diagnosis and selective mutism, but will do so.<br />
Very best wishes<br />
Michael<br />
PS this weekend&#8217;s post is about stammering.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Tim Dunkerley				</title>
				<link>/2013/11/did-you-ever-wake-up-with-them-bullfrogs-on-your-mind/#comment-7835</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim Dunkerley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 20:08:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=843#comment-7835</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[What a lovely story. You had me picturing George as a boy for the longest time. Your storytelling skills match you analysis of childhood and language.

Interesting Rory facts. His guitar: legendarily worn and stripped of most of it&#039;s paint . Allegedly, according to Donal, his brother, manager and and keeper of his physical and spiritual legacy... The paint peeled off because Rory&#039;s bloodtype gave him particularly acidic sweat which stripped the paint...He did play and sweat a lot so it may well be true.
Other great Rory fact: Jimi Hendix was asked what it was like to be the best guitarist in the world. He replied (again allegedly)&quot;I don&#039;t know man, you should ask Rory Gallagher&quot; I believe it and I believe he wasn&#039;t being ironic.
TD]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What a lovely story. You had me picturing George as a boy for the longest time. Your storytelling skills match you analysis of childhood and language.</p>
<p>Interesting Rory facts. His guitar: legendarily worn and stripped of most of it&#8217;s paint . Allegedly, according to Donal, his brother, manager and and keeper of his physical and spiritual legacy&#8230; The paint peeled off because Rory&#8217;s bloodtype gave him particularly acidic sweat which stripped the paint&#8230;He did play and sweat a lot so it may well be true.<br />
Other great Rory fact: Jimi Hendix was asked what it was like to be the best guitarist in the world. He replied (again allegedly)&#8221;I don&#8217;t know man, you should ask Rory Gallagher&#8221; I believe it and I believe he wasn&#8217;t being ironic.<br />
TD</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
			</channel>
</rss>
